The Leo E. Gibson MD Papers
Archives and Special Collections at the SUNY Upstate Health Sciences Library
The Leo E. Gibson MD Papers
1920-1966
SUNY Upstate Medical University 766 Irving Avenue Syracuse, NY 13210
Gibson, Leo
.79 linear feet
This collection contains the papers of Leo E. Gibson, who graduated from Syracuse University College of Medicine in 1920 and was a urologist. The collection has four series: Printed Materials, Subject Files, Memorabilia, and Photographs.
FIC2017.0010
Biographical Note
Leo Eaton Gibson (1894-1966) was born in the town of Willet and attended Whitney Point High School before receiving his B.S. in 1917 and M.D. in 1920 from Syracuse University. His internship was at St. Josephs on Staten Island from 1919 to 1922, and his residency in urology was at Massachusetts General Hospital in Boston. During World War II, he served in the military as a surgeon for the US Public Health Service and completed postgraduate education at the Brady Urological Institute at John Hopkins. He married Pauline Remington, and they had two sons, Eaton and Peter. He was president of the Medical Society of the State of New York and Onondaga County Medical Society, a member of Alpha Kappa Kappa, and a consulting urologist at the Upstate Medical Center, St. Joseph's Hospital and Syracuse Memorial Hospital. From 1927 to 1954, he was a member of the Syracuse University College of Medicine faculty and a clinical professor emeritus until his death in 1966.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the papers of Leo E. Gibson, who graduated from Syracuse University College of Medicine in 1920 and was a urologist. There are four series in this collection.
Printed Materials: these documents were accumulated by Dr. Gibson on a variety of medical subjects primarily in the 1950s.
Subject Files: these materials include papers on the Medical Society of the State of New York, the Urologists Correspondence Club, and Dr. Gibson’s urology clippings and drafts of publications.
Memorabilia: Dr. Gibson's certificates, licenses, and diploma are in this series.
Photographs: this series contains glass lantern slides that relate to Dr. Gibson’s urology studies.
Arrangement of the Collection
The Leo E. Gibson MD Papers have been arranged into four series.
Separated Material
Dr. Gibson’s medicine kit has been removed to the objects collection.
Subject and Genre Headings
Gibson, Leo E., 1894-1966; Medical education; Medical Society of the State of New York (1807- ); Syracuse University, College of Medicine; Urology
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Acquisition Information
Unknown.
Inventory
- Printed Materials
  - Free choice and freedom, medical education, insurance, socialism and socialized medicine, welfare and social security, aging, and public health clippings, reports, publications, press releases, pamphlets, and speeches and addresses, including Health Services in Norway., 1937; 1946-1962; 3 folders (Box Box 1)
  - Business and medicine clippings, publications, pamphlets, and speeches and addresses., 1953-1959 (Box Box 1)
  - Peace and war publications, clippings, pamphlets, poems, and speeches and addresses., 1951; 1954; 1956; 1959 (Box Box 1)
  - Granular urethritis publications and clippings., 1951; 1958; 1959 (Box Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous and history clippings, publications, pamphlets, and speeches and addresses., 1957; undated (Box Box 1)
- Subject Files
  - Urology medical publications, clippings, and drafts of writings for publications., 1929; 1942; 1948; undated (Box Box 1)
  - Urologists Correspondence Club newsletters., 1963-1966 (Box Box 1)
  - Medical Society of the State of New York reports, clippings, newsletters, and speeches and addresses., 1953; 1955-1957; 1960 (Box Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Certificate of residence at Staten Island Hospital in Richmond County, New York., 1920 (Box Box 1)
  - Certificate of membership for the Association of Reserve Officers., 1945 (Box Box 1)
  - Certificate of Appreciation for service as member of Selective Service System., 1958 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Certificate of Appreciation for service as member of Selective Service System., 1963 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Certificate of appointment as examining physician to local board., 1942 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Certificate of appointment as intern at St. Joseph’s Hospital., 1920 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - New York license to practice medicine and surgery., 1920 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Appointment as Major in Army Medical Corps., 1941 (Box Box 1)
  - American Board of Urology certification., 1937 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Certification for term as house surgeon at the Staten Island Hospital, New York City., 1921 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Certificate of commendation from the bureau of medicine and surgery, United States Navy for education of Navy V-12 students in medical corps during World War II., 1945 (Box Box 1)
  - Certification as founder member of the US committee in support of the scientific and educational objectives of the World Medical Association., 1957 (Box Box 1)
  - Election as fellow to the Academy International of Medicine certificate., 1944 (Box Box 1)
  - American Urological Association membership certificate., 1929 (Box Box 1)
  - American College of Surgeons Fellow certificate., 1929 (Box Box 1)
  - Board of Ambulance Service certification for ambulance surgeon duties at Staten Island Hospital, New York City., 1921 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Medical advisor local board no. 58 appointment certificate., 1948 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Resident surgeon on urological service at Massachusetts General Hospital certification., 1926 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Certificate of appointment as surgeon for the reserve of the United States public health service., 1943 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
  - Syracuse University College of Medicine diploma for Leo E. Gibson., 1920 (Box Oversize Case 8, Shelf 2)
- Photographs
  - Portrait prints and negatives of Leo Gibson., undated (Box Box 1)
  - Glass lantern slides of x-rays, drawings, and photographs of internal organs., undated (Box Box 2)
  - Glass lantern slides of prostate pathology x-rays and drawings., undated (Box Box 2)
  - Glass lantern slides of prostatic resection cast study text, tables, x-rays, photographs, and drawings., undated (Box Box 2)